Southwest Folklore Center Cassette Recordings Collection, 1975-1995
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Southwest Folklore Center Cassette Recordings Collection, 1975-1995
SWF 009
University of Arizona. Southwest Folklore Center.
Cassette recordings of gospel music, country and western music, Mexican American and Native American music, cowboy songs, and interviews with Arizona residents. Most cassettes are commercially produced.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
Restricted. Researchers must use copies of all cassettes when they are available. An item level listing of all cassettes in the collection is available at the end of this document. Duplicates of the cassettes are numbered to correspond to the call numbers of the original cassettes.
Historical Note
The Southwest Folklore Center was founded in 1979 upon the dissolution of the University of Arizona Folklore Committee. Since then it has served as an archive for folklore material. Its activities include actively researching and collecting information about Arizona's folk communities, generating outreach programs, and coordinating folk activities throughout the state.
Arrangement
Arranged according to accession into the collection.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists chiefly of commercially produced cassette recordings of gospel music, country and western music, Native American music and cowboy songs. Performers include many Native American musicians from Arizona. Music performed by Native American musicians and published by Canyon Records of Phoenix, Arizona, comprises a large portion of the cassette recordings. The collection includes cassettes of music written and performed by Lalo Guerrero, Mexican American musician born in Tucson, Arizona.
The collection includes interviews with Arizona residents, folk artists and musicians, and recordings of performances at annual cowboy poetry gatherings.
Access Terms
Folk music
Corridos
Cowboys - Songs and music
Cowboys -- West (U.S.) -- Poetry
Folk music – Arizona
Folk songs, Spanish
Indians of Mexico – Music
Indians of North America - Arizona – Music
Indians of North America – Southwest
Mariachi music
Mexican Americans – Music
Organ music
Polkas
Apache Indians – Music
Blackfeet Indians – Music
Hopi Indians – Music
Navajo Indians – Music
Pima Indians – Music
Tohono O'odham Indians – Music
Waila (Chicken scratch music)
Revolutionary ballads and songs – Mexico
Guerrero, Lalo, 1916-
University of Arizona. Southwest Folklore Center
Container List
- Interview with Everett Brisendine, Brisendine, Everett, 1980 February 26; Chino Valley, AZ., February 26, 1980; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Information from acquisitions file... Interview with Everett Brisendine, rawhide braider, cowboy and poet by James S. Griffith and Larry Evers... Transcription of interview includes poems: Just me -- Standin' nightguard -- To a wonderful lady -- In memory of a pardner -- A Cowboy is going to town -- Signs of the times -- The Sub-divisions -- My toeholt in the foothills -- These old hands -- Life is like a game of poker -- Never give up -- My choctaw -- Chuckwagon cook --Collected by James S. Griffith and Larry Evers; SWF 80.2/C.1
- Interview with Rev. Hilaseo Howard, Hilaseo, Howard, Rev., 1979 December 15; Eloy, AZ., December 15, 1979; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisition file 80.3: James S. Griffith and Worth Lang interview Reverend Hilaseo Howard of Eloy, Arizona, December 15, 1979... Stories include one about a rabbit running a race with a hedgehog, Howard's life story, a story about a white man trying to scare a black man, a story about a white girl with father's stallion, a story about Truth and Lie's clothing... transcription located in file 80.3/C.1.T...Collected by James S. Griffith and Worth Lang; SWF 80.3/C.1
- Interview with Edith Sayre Auslander, Auslander, Edith Sayre, 1980 December 15; Tucson, AZ., March 7, 1980; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Information from acquisitions file... tape contains interview with Edith Sayre Auslander by James S. Griffith about Mexican folklore including: La Llorena; Wings on bad children; El Tiradito; Promesas... Transcription of interview in acquisitions file. Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 80.4/C.1
- Interview with Slim Harper and Rocky Harper, Harper, Slim and Rocky Harper, 1980 August 30; Huachuca City, AZ., August 30, 1980; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Transcription of interview in acquisitions file... Recording contains interview with Slim Harper and Rocky Harper by James S. Griffith about cowboys and cowboy life... Donated by James S. Griffith; SWF 80.6/C.1
- Entrevista con Lidia Mendoza, Mendoza, Linda, 1977 October; Marriott Hotel,[Tucson, AZ]., October, 1977; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisition file 80.7: Tape contains Lisa W. Cobb's (anthropology student, Pima Community College) interview with Lidia Mendoza, in Spanish, at Tucson's Marriott Hotel, October 7, 1977... File 80.7/C.1.T includes transcription in Spanish...; SWF 80.7/C.1
- Interview with Elizabeth Konuch, Konuch, Elizabeth, 1980 May 1; Tempe, AZ., May 1, 1980; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisitions file 80.8: "Interview concerns Mrs. Konuch's family tradition (Czech) of Easter egg decorating; some life history... Also a discussion of her mother's beaded, embroidered wedding cap... transcription located in file 80.8/C.1.T...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 80.8/C.1
- Interview with Clay Ramsey, Ramsey, Clay, 1980 December 11; Phoenix, AZ., December 11, 1980; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisiton file 80.9: James S. Griffith interviews Clay Ramsey, at his Phoenix home, December 11, 1980... Topics include the history of Ramsey's involvememt in Old-Timer Record Company of Phoenix; the general Phoenix square dance scene of the 1940's and 1950's; local fiddlers... Transcription is located in file 80.9/C.1.T...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 80.9/C.1
- Interview with Slim Kite, Kite, Slim (Luther), 1981 Februrary 25; Chino Valley, AZ., Februrary 25, 1981; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisitions file 81.4: James S. Griffith interviews Slim Kite in Chino Valley, Februrary 25, 1981... Transcription located in acquisitions file 81.4/C.1.T...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 81.4/C.1
- Interview with Dick Denny, Denny, Dick, 1981 Februrary 26; Skull Valley, AZ., February 26, 1981; 1 sound cassette (60 min.), analog; NOTES: Information from acquisitions file... Interview with Dick Denny by James S. Griffith... Transcription of interview in acquisitions file includes lyrics to songs... The Hophead -- Platonia -- Utah -- Zebra dun -- Strawberry roan -- Stories: [Cattle and a frog] -- [Biographical stories]...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 81.5/C.1
- Interview with Elizabeth Franklin, Franklin, Elizabeth, 1981 April 9; Tucson, AZ., April 9, 1981; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Transcription of interview in file, 81.6/C.1.T... Interview by Tatjana Swihart with Elizabeth Franklin discusses fairies and her beliefs about fairies... This tape and transcription were part of an English assignment at the University of Arizona......Collected by Tatjana Swihart; SWF 81.6/C.1
- Interview with Anne Meyer, Meyer, Anne, 1981 June 2; Tucson, AZ., June 2, 1981; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From file 81.12/C.1.T... Interview conducted at Anne Meyer's house, Tucson, Arizona... Meyers discusses Ukranian egg decorating and embroidery... transcription in file... tape and transcription were part of an English class assignment, University of Arizona...Collected by Claire Rosenberg; SWF 81.12/C.1
- Interview with Ernie Nelson, Nelson, Ernie, 1980 December 3; Tucson, AZ., December 3, 1980; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisition file, 81.13/M-1: The interview was conducted at the University of Arizona Folk Lore Center... Interview was with Ernie Nelson, senior member of the Finery Cross Peabrook Society and The Seven Pipers, both of Tucson, Arizona. Mr. Nelson discusses the history of the groups, bagpipe playing and music... Transcript of interview is in acquisitions file... Tape and transcript part of an assignment for English 441, Spring, 1981, at the University of Arizona...Collected by Terri Fowlie; SWF 81.13/C.1
- Songs by Carol Huish, Huish, Carol, 1981 November 8; Douglas, AZ., November 8, 1981; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: Tape contains nine unaccompanied ballads sung by Carol Huish at her home... recorded by her daughter, Sharon Huish as part of an assignment for English 449 at the University of Arizona...Collected by Sharon Huish; SWF 81.17/C.1
- Interview with Marion Maxwell, Maxwell, Marion, 1980 September 4; Springerville, Az., September 4, 1980; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: Cassette contains interview with Marion Maxwell about the Maxwell family band (White Mountain Orchestra)...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 81.20/C.1
- Interview with Jimenez Heliodoro, Heliodoro, Jimenez, 1975 January; January, 1975; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Tape contains a report of a visit to Jimenez Heliodoro's pottery shop in Nogales...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.8/C.1
- Interview with Jimenez Heliodoro, Heliodoro, Jimenez, 1981 September 6; Tumacacori, AZ., September 6, 1981; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisition Inventory: Tape contains interview by James S. Griffith with Heliodoro regarding his apprenticeship as a potter in Hermosillo, Sonora, Mexico in 1932... In Spanish... Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.8/C.2
- Interview with Arturo Montoya and Anne Meyer, Montoya, Arturo and Anne Meyer, 1979 September 9; [September 9, 1979]; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: Side one contains an interview by James S. Griffith with Arturo Montoya at his home, about his talents as an artist/sculptor his dedication of these talents to the Yaqui culture... Side two contains an interview by James S. Griffith with Anne Meyer about Ukrainian crafts, including pysanky (decorated eggs), embroidery, and woodcarving...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.9/C.1
- Interview about flour tortillas with Ramona Alegria and Consuelo Martinez, Alegria, Ramona and Consuelo Martinez, 1981 June 6; Tumacacori, AZ., June 6, 1981; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: Interview taped at Tumacacori, Arizona... interviews discuss flour tortilla making...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.10/C.1
- Interview with Maria Rodriquez, Rodriguez, Maria, 1981 June 20; Tumacacori. AZ., June 20, 1981; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: interview with Maria Rodriguez discusses tortilla making... taped at Tumacacori, Arizona...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.11/C.1
- Interview with Wade Mainer and Bill Hensley, Mainer, Wade and Bill Hensley, 1982 February 16; February 16, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: tape contains an interview recorded at James S. Griffith's house... includes banjo tunings, some songs and a discussion of the banjo...; SWF 82.12/C.1
- Songs from I.D. Jones and Kenneth Jones, Jones, I.D. and Kenneth Jones, 1982 May 6; San Simon, AZ., May 6, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: tape includes "songs and short interview with I.D. Jones (aged 94) and son, Kenneth Jones, outside their home near San Simon, Arizona"... Acqusitions Inventory indicates tape is of poor quality...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.14/C.1
- Notes from interview with Mrs. Alexandra Romaneko, Romaneko, Mrs. Alexandra, 1982 April 28; San Simon, AZ., May 6, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: Mrs. Romaneko is a Ukranian pysanky (decorated egg) maker, from Tucson, Arizona. Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.18/C.1
- Interview with Jesus Leon Gutierrez, Gutierrez, Jesus Leon, 1982 May 15; May 15, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisition Inventory... Sr. Leon is from Barrio Cruzero, Imuris, Sonora, Mexico... Sr. Leon discusses making articulos religiosos (religious articles) and a puppet show (títeres) his father ran in Sonora... In Spanish...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.19/C.1
- Mormon Cowboy, Gutierrez, Sauders, Charlie, [198?]; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisitions file 82.27: "...tape sent in response to letter in the Globe "Silver Belt" inquiring about the song, "Mormon Cowboy." Contains spoken introduction; a few biographical details; a performance of the song; a request for a more complete text; and a return address"... Transcription located in file 82.27/C.1...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.27/C.1
- Interview with Josefina Gallegos, Gallegos, Josefina, 1982 April 4; [April 4, 1982]; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisition file 82.28: "Fr. Charles Polzer and Bernard Fontana, both of the University of Arizona interviewed Josefina Gallegos, "Chata", the sacristana of San Ignacio de Caborica, Sonara and her sister [Teresa Gallegos] in Sra. Gallegos' house on Palm /Sunday, April 4, 1982... [Gallegos discussed] San Ignacio's traditional Holy Week as it was celebrated in the 1930's... Interview in Spanish... Transcript in file 82.28/C.1.T...Collected by Charles Polzer and Bernard Fontana; SWF 82.28/C.1
- Interview with Ruth Dyer, Dyer, Ruth, 1982 July 17; Tucson, AZ., July 17, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisition file 82.29: Interview by James S. Griffith with Ruth Dyer at her home in Tucson, Arizona, regarding the making of rag rugs and tatting... Transcript located in file 82.29/C.1.T...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.29/C.1
- St. Johns Four Wards Variety Show: Memories of the past, St. Johns Four Wards Variety Show, 1982 July 22; St. Johns, AZ., July 22, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Recording of the St. John's Four Wards Variety Show, "Memories of the Past," held on July 22, 1982, as part of St. John's Pioneer Days Celebration. Notes in the Acquisition Inventory indicate that the recording quality is poor, and that parts of the program were omitted... Notes in the acquisition file indicate that a printed program is available in the Archive's St. Johns Pioneer Day, 1982, file...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.30/C.1
- Interview with Lydia Mendoza, Mendoza, Lydia, 1982 September 30; Washington, D.C., Recorded at the Ethnic Music Conference, September 30, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Acqusition files contain transcription of interview with Lydia Mendoza by James S. Griffith... In Spanish and English...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.32/C.1
- Oral History of the Pueblo Opodepe, Sonora, 1974 April 8; Washington, D.C., Recorded at the Ethnic Music Conference, September 30, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Information from Acqusitions Inventory: tape contains interview with an elderly gentleman by James S. Griffith and Arturo Oliveros about the history of Opodepe... Discussion involves a tour of the church; the village Easter ceremony and an Apache attack of the town during Holy week ... In Spanish...Collected by James S. Griffith and Arturo Oliveros; SWF 82.32/C.1
- Interview with Norma Reynolds, Reynolds, Norma, 1977; Tucson, AZ., 1977; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: tape contains an interview by James S. Griffith with Norma Reynolds about her life and music... interview conducted at Reynold's home... "Reynolds has appeared at the Tucson Meet Yourself Festivals and tapes of those appearances are available in the Archive"...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.34/C.1
- Interview [with] Doña Luz Valenzuela, Valenzuela, Doña Luz, 1978 March 8; Tucson, AZ., March 8, 1978; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions Inventory: interview conducted by James S. Griffith and Richard Morales with Doña Luz Valenzuela in her house, March 8, 1978, Tucson, Arizona, on the subject of holiday foods, especially foods served during Lent. Collected by James S. Griffith and Richard Morales; SWF 82.35/C.1
- Interview with Alfonso Flores and Tina Salcido, Flores, Alfonso and Tina Salcido, 1981 May 5; Tubac, AZ., May 5, 1981; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Acquisitions file contains transcriptions of interviews by James S. Griffith, with Alfonso Flores, a woodcarver, and Tina Salcido, a corn tortilla maker... Flores was interviewed at his home in Tubac, Arizona... Salcido was interviewed at Tumacacori National Monument... Interviews are about their lives and crafts... In Spanish...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.37/C.1
- Interview with Ernesto and Gloria Delgadillo, Delgadillo, Ernesto and Gloria, 1982 December 7; Tucson, AZ., December 7, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Acquisitions file contains transcription of interview with Ernesto and Gloria Delgradillo by James S. Griffith... Interview was recorded at the Delgadillo's home and discusses piñata making skills, their piñata business and tradition... In Spanish...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.43/C.1
- Interview with Cruz Lopez, Velasquez, Cruz Lopez, 1982 December 9; [Sonora, Mexico], December 9, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From Acquisitions file 82.44: "Interview by James S. Griffith (Richard Morales holding mike, asking occasional questions) and Cruz Lopez Velasquez. The interview took place in Sr. Lopez' store, where he and his wife make and sell plaster cast statues of sacred personages"... File 82.44/C.1.T includes transcription... Interview in Spanish...Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 82.44/C.1
- Interview with Pete Castillo, Castillo, Pete, 1982 December 29; December 29, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisition file 83.1: "Interview by James S. Griffith and Richard Morales with Pete Castillo of Marana, AZ... Includes Pete's recollections of Juan Johnson, a Black cowboy who worked in the Sasco-Silver Bell-Redrock area in the 1920's and was a pal of Pete's; Pete's story of the life and death of El Texano, a legendary stage robber in the Tucson-Picacho area [bibliography included]... Transcript located in file 83.1/C.1... Interview in Spanish...Collected by James S. Griffith and Richard Morales; SWF 83.1/C.1
- Frank Grinnell plays banjo, Ginnell, Frank, [AZ], Copyright by Frank Grinnell, [198-?]; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Photograph of Frank Grinnell on cover... From acquisition file 83.4: "Tape... recorded by Mr. Grinnell of himself playing tenor banjo... Biographical information included as well as an article from the 'Green Valley News/Sun'"... File 83.4/C.1.T includes transcription... Musicians include: Frank Grinnell; Lynn Farone, vocal; Tom Deane, bass; Manny Truman and the Bourbon Street Dixieland Band... Heart of my heart -- China boy -- Battle hymn of the Republic -- Birth of the blues -- Basin Street -- Manicure -- China Town -- Lover, come back to me -- Old rocking chair's got me -- I know that you know -- Back home again in Indiana -- Corn relish -- "Up the lazy river" --; SWF 83.4/C.1
- Hurley - Leta - Mollie, McCombs, Hurley, 1993 January; [January], 1993; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: From acquisition file 83.5: "Fiddle tunes and songs learned by Jurley McCombs from his father...[tunes] have been in the family for four generations in Missouri... file contains a two-page manuscript, in pencil, of the "The Dying Cowboy" as sung by Leta McCombs... Transcription located in file 83.5/C.1.T...Waltz in G -- Waltz in D -- Hoedown in D -- Hoedown in D -- "Rabbit[?] where's your mammy" -- The Dying cowboy -- "Dying Ranger", (Leta McCombs, Fred and Molly Warren, accompanied on banjo by Hurley McCombs) --Collected by James S. Griffith; SWF 83.5/C.1
- [Built] on a slim foundation of fact: A look at cowboy humor, James S. Griffith, 1983; [Tucson, AZ., 1983]; 1 sound cassette (28:45 min.), analog; NOTES: From acquisitions file, 83.6: "...copy of the program, 'Built on a slim foundation of fact: a look at cowboy humor' which was produced in cooperation with KUAT AM. It is a half hour show which has received national distribution and aired July, 1982. The program was produced in May of 1982 by James S. Griffith and Cephas Bowles of KUAT. It features stories, tall tales, and a song performed by five old-time Arizona cowboys: the late Van Holyoak of Clay Springs; Everett Brisendine of Chino Valley; Marvin Bennett of Mayer; Gail Gardner of Prescott; and Dick Denny who is now a resident of Australia. James S. Griffith serves as narrator and the music is provided by Tucon's own Ed Smith and Dean Armstrong"... Transcript located in file 83.6/C.1.T...; SWF 83.6/C.1
- Dick Denny correspondence tape, Denny, Dick, 1982 December 25; December 25, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog; NOTES: Information from Acqusitions Inventory, "Dick Denny, an old time central Arizona rancher, comments on the radio program, 'A slim foundation of fact...' which featured one of his narratives. He describes Queensland, Australia, where he has settled and reminisces about family ranching"...; SWF 83.7/C.1
- Interview with Don Pedro Rodriguez, Rodríguez, Don Pedro, 1983 February 13; Sonoita, AZ., February 13, 1983; 1 sound cassette, analog, dolby stereo; NOTES: From Acquisition Inventory, tape includes interview and songs by Don Pedro Rodríguez, harpist...This is a dub of a tape collected by Phillip Sonningham...Original tape was recorded at the Steak Out Restaurant in Sonoita, Arizona...Songs include, Amor de madre -- Las Perlitas -- 1181 -- Serenata huasteca (huapango) -- Torreon alerdo -- Campanitas (polka) -- La Norteña -- El Costeño -- Nube gris --; SWF 83.8/C.7
- Interview with José Pomposa Salaza Araiza of Nogales, Araiza, José Pmposa Salazar, 1982 February 27; Tucson, AZ., February 27, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog, vol. 1; NOTES: Interview with Bill Hensley of Tucson...Collected by Keith and Kathy Cunningham...Includes his life story, banjo tunes, and songs...Information in Acquisition files includes transcription of tape...Collector: Keith Cunningham and Kathy Cunningham.; SWF 83.12/C.1
- Interview with Bill Hensley of Tucson, Hensley, Bill, 1982 February 27; Tucson, AZ., February 27, 1982; 1 sound cassette, analog, vol. 2; NOTES: Collected by Keith and Kathy Cunningham... Interview with Bill Hensley of Tucson, Arizona about his life, banjo tunes and songs... Information in acquisition file includes transcript...Collector: Keith Cunningham and Kathy Cunningham.; SWF 83.12/C.2
- Guest ranches in Arizona, Agins, Singin' Sam, 1979; 1979; 1 sound cassette, analog, vol. 1; NOTES: Acquisition files include a transcription... tape contains an interview between James S. Griffith and Sam Agins and a lecture by Sam Agins about his singing career at guest ranches in Arizona... lecture was given in the fall of 1979...Collector: James S. Griffith; SWF 83.21/C.1
- Guest ranches in Arizona, Agins, Singin' Sam, 1979; 1979; 1 sound cassette, analog, vol. 2; NOTES: Acquisition files include a transcription... tape contains an interview between James S. Griffith and Sam Agins and a lecture by Sam Agins about his singing career at guest ranches in Arizona... lecture was given in the fall of 1979...Collector: James S. Griffith; SWF 83.21/C.2